A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests, Series E FA314
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Cultural Interests, Series E
1888-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
Rockefeller, John D.
Spelman family
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller, Winthrop
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Rockefeller family
Mauze, Abby Rockefeller
Aldrich, Nelson W. (Nelson Wilmarth)
Rockefeller, David
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
FA314
177 document box(es)
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records are arranged by subject matter in 27 series. Most of these series are wholly or partially open for research. The series are:
A John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; C Business Interests; D Civic Interests; E Cultural Interests; F Economic Reform Interests; G Educational Interests; H Friends and Services; I Homes; J Housing Interests; K Medical Interests; L Real Estate; M Maps and Memorabilia; N Religious Interests; O Rockefeller Boards; P Welfare - General Files; Q World Affairs; R Welfare - Youth Files; S Documents; T Public Relations; U Public Land Law Review Commission; V Greenrock; W Properties; X Costume Collection; Y Media; Z John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal; AA Abby Aldrich Rockefeller; AC Abby Rockefeller Mauzé
Biographical/Historical note
The central figure in the creation and operation of the Standard Oil Company during its rise to the top of the petroleum industry, John D. Rockefeller (JDR) established for the family a leading role in business and philanthropy. From the days of his earliest employment, Rockefeller, a devout Baptist, was generous in his giving to worthy causes, especially those of a religious nature. During the 1890s he developed an orderly system of philanthropic giving through an office staff that included his close advisor, Frederick T. Gates (1853-1929) and his son, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (1874-1960). With the advise of these and other associates, Rockefeller established the University of Chicago, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), the Rockefeller Foundation, and other philanthropic organizations working nationally and internationally in the fields of education, religion, and health. Rockefeller's total donations to philanthropic endeavors are estimated to have been $540 million.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.) joined his father's office on October 1, 1897. He oversaw the expansion and diversification of the philanthropic work begun by his father. During his lifetime, the younger Rockefeller gave more than $537 million to educational, religious, cultural, medical, and other charitable projects.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and his wife, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (1874-1948), passed the Rockefeller philanthropic impulse on to their children. John D. 3rd (1906-1978), Nelson A. (1908-1979), Laurance S. (1910-2004), Winthrop (1912-1973), and David (1915-) further expanded and diversified Rockefeller influence and interests, establishing their own philanthropic organizations, most notably the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1940), and becoming more active politically.
Scope and Contents note
The Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller (OMR) materials document the increasing role assumed by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. in the management of Rockefeller affairs and amply document his business and philanthropic affairs. They also chronicle the entrance of JDR Jr.'s sons, John D. 3rd, Nelson A., Laurance S., Winthrop, and David, into the world of business, philanthropy, civic leadership, and politics as they joined the office.
This material contains correspondence, reports, pamphlets, memoranda, deeds, maps, contracts, reports, minutes, charters, certificates of incorporation, clippings, diaries, notebooks, calendars, and memorabilia.
There is a microfilm card index of personal and institutional names.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 02
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in nineteen sections:
Chautauqua Institute; Historical Monuments; Libraries; Memorials; Milbank Memorial Fund; Motion Pictures; Museums; Music; Organizations and Parks; Palisades Interstate Park; Plant, Flower, and Fruit Guild; Radio and Television; Restorations; Chinese Restorations; French Restorations; Old Ironsides; Colonial Williamsburg; Theatre; Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents note
The Cultural Interests series reflects the Rockefeller family's involvement and contributions in the areas of the arts, museums, parks, and historic restorations. The series contains correspondence between members of the Rockefeller family and the Family Office Staff on the one hand, and officials and members of the various institutions and organizations on the other. Most of the material concerns unsolicited appeals for donations. Some members of the family were also members of or were active in several of the organizations, and some of the correspondence reflects this activity.
The family members who figure most prominently in this series are John D. Rockefeller Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, and David Rockefeller. John D. Rockefeller Sr., Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Winthrop Rockefeller, Abby Rockefeller Mauzé, Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller, Mary French Rockefeller, Margaret (Peggy) McGrath Rockefeller, and Martha Baird Rockefeller also appear.
The Colonial Williamsburg section of the Cultural Interests series comprises 29 manuscript boxes of material covering the years 1926-1961. While this section does not cover all aspects of the restoration from the initiation of the idea in 1926 through John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s death in 1960, most major facets of this massive project are included. The main focus of this material is on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s participation in the origin and development of the idea of restoring the Tidewater city to its authentic mid-eighteenth-century condition. There are folders for each of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts, which totaled over $450 million by 1960. The financial history of the restoration can be traced through a series of Treasurer's reports, operating budgets, and annual reports, as well as memoranda between John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Kenneth Chorley, Carlisle Humelsine, Vernon Geddy, and John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
The quality and inclusiveness of the documentary material drops sharply after 1954, as a consequence of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s increasing age, the retirement of Kenneth Chorley, the modest financial success of the restoration, and the resignation of John D. Rockefeller 3rd from the Chairmanship. This last event provides an interesting counterpoint to the main theme of the Colonial Williamsburg files and one fully covered by the documents included here. John D. Rockefeller 3rd supported his father's efforts to complete the historical restoration, but he also hoped to use Williamsburg for broader educational and less antiquarian purposes. During the entire period of his tenure as Chairman (1939-1953), but especially during the years 1948-1952, he sought to convince his father and fellow trustees that Williamsburg could play a central role in the effort to revitalize American democracy and to remind the country of its political and economic heritage. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's resignation stemmed from John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s growing reluctance to see any resources diverted from the central objective of restoring Williamsburg.
Related Archival Materials note
For additional information about Palisades Interstate Park, see also the Mark M. Jones Papers at the Rockefeller Archive Center.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records include: FA310 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Sr.
FA312 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Business Interests
FA313 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Civic Interests
FA315 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Economic Reform Interests
FA316 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Educational Interests
FA317 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Friends and Services
FA318 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Homes
FA319 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Housing Interests
FA320 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Medical Interests
FA321 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Real Estate
FA322 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Maps and Memorabilia
FA323 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests
FA324 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Rockefeller Boards
FA325 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - General Files
FA326 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, World Affairs
FA327 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare - Youth Files
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations
FA333 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Costume Collection
FA334 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Media
FA335 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Personal
FA336 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller
FA337 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Abby Rockefeller Mauze
United States; Travel; Urban renewal; Urban policy; World War II; World War I; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Education; Education -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Folk art; Government policy; Public welfare; Religion; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Child welfare; Civic improvement; Business enterprises, Foreign; Capital investments; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Arts; Business; Economics; Economic policy; Economic development; Art; International education; International relations; International cooperation; International economic relations; Maternal health services; Medical care; International relations -- United States; Juvenile delinquency; Medical sciences; New York (N.Y.); Medical education; Medical research; Performing arts; New York (State); Philanthropy -- United States; Parks -- New York (State); Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; Philanthropy; Public policy; Public health administration; Public health; Prohibition; Rockefeller University; Bureau of Social Hygiene. (New York, N.Y.); Spelman Fund; Rockefeller Brothers Fund; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller Center; China Medical Board (U.S); Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Fosdick, Raymond B. (Raymond Blaine); Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Standard Oil Company; General Education Board. (New York, N.Y.); International Education Board; Sealantic Fund, New York; Davison Fund
- Chautauqua Institution
  - Chautauqua Institution, 1919-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Invitations to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to speak at Chautauqua declined; appeals for aid declined. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Arthur E. Bestar, Arthur W. Packard.
    File Plan note
    182
  - Chautauqua Institution - Pledges and Payments, 1919-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contributions by John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Chautauqua Institution - Gift, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. $15,000 gift to reduce indebtedness.
  - Historical Monuments, Inc., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    A proposed non-profit corporation to undertake the restoration and preservation of historic buildings in New York state. Corporation not formed, but a bill passed in New York legislature permitting historical societies to charge admission. This was done for the Philipse Manor House while it was run by the Tarrytown Historical Society. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Hugh Grant Rowell, Thomas Dewey.
    167
- Libraries
  - Libraries - New York Public Library, 1916-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions toward operating deficits, endowment, Donnell Branch on West 53rd Street, and general purposes. Contributions by Mary French Rockefeller; various members of family send books to library as gifts. Studies of library operation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Beardsley Ruml, Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Mary French Rockefeller.
    183
  - Libraries - New York Public Library, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Libraries - New York Public Library, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 0006A)
  - Libraries - New York Public Library - Pledges, 1921-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift of $3,000,000 for endowment.
  - Libraries - New York Public Library - Music Museum and Library, 1924-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Appeals for contributions to music department of library; plans for a music library museum. Nelson A. Rockefeller gave $10,000 toward promotion of idea, but it never became a reality. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, C. S. Smith.
  - Libraries - New York Public Library - Beardsley Ruml Report, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Financial and management study of library operations; led to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s 1922-23 pledge. Report in file is not the final copy. Correspondents include Beardsley Ruml.
  - Libraries - Paris Library School, American Library in Paris, 1924-1960 (Box 2, Folder 0009A)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to assist in training French librarians in American library methods. By 1944 School had become an American library in Paris. Nelson A. Rockefeller contribution, 1946. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Kenneth Chorley, Arthur W. Packard, Nelson A. Rockefeller.
    183.1
  - Libraries - Paris Library School, American Library in Paris, 1924-1960 (Box 2, Folder 0009AB)
    David Rockefeller contributions in 1948 and 1952. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Libraries - Paris Library School, American Library in Paris - Pledge and Payment, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge of $37,500 for this Paris project of American Library Association.
  - Libraries - Lakewood Library, 1905-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    John D. Rockefeller contributes $3,000 toward library in Lakewood, NJ: building, furniture, books. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller.
    183.2
  - Libraries - Library of Congress, 1915-1932 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution of $700,000 toward source material in American history and enlargement of bibliographic apparatus in library. Nelson A. Rockefellers contribution towards purchase of "Alice in Wonderland" manuscript for gift to England. Reports on library activity. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Thomas B. Appleget, Arthur W. Packard, Luther Evans, Herbert Putnam.
    183.3
  - Libraries - Library of Congress, 1933-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Libraries - Library of Congress - Aldrich Papers, 1938-1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Arrangements for depositing papers of Senator Nelson Aldrich in Library. Restrictions on use.
  - Libraries - Library of Congress - Gift of John D. Rockefeller Papers, 1945-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Discussion of possibility of sending John D. Rockefeller papers to Library; no action taken.
  - Libraries - Rigot Property - Offer to the University of Geneva, 1937-1943 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Decision to dispose of property by giving it to University; details on purpose and conditions of gift; letters of appreciation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Thomas M. Debevoise, A. W. Sweetser.
    183.41
  - Libraries - Rigot Property - Offer to the University of Geneva, 1944-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Libraries - League of Nations Library - Rigot Property, 1930-1939 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. purchased property to protect site of League; use of property; decision to give property to University of Geneva. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, Phillip Keebler, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, B. Turnbull, A. W. Sweetser.
    183.4
  - Libraries - League of Nations Library - Rigot Property, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Libraries - Library of the League of Nations, 1927-1955, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $2,000,000 to construct and endow library at Geneva; progress of library, war-time problems; transfer of library from League to United Nations. Correspondents include Raymond B. Fosdick, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, A. W. Sweetser.
  - Libraries - Library of the League of Nations - Pledge, October 4, 1927, 1927-1934 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Copy of pledge, payments; gift tax problem.
  - Libraries - Library for American Studies in Italy, 1918-1933 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributed $4,500 to promote better understanding of U.S. in Italy. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods.
    183.5
  - Libraries - Miscellaneous, 1922-1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Gifts of books to some libraries; declinations of appeals for aid. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Dana S. Creel.
    183.9
  - Libraries - Miscellaneous, 1922-1962 (Box 3, Folder 0023A)
    Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Libraries - American Library Association, 1927-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Libraries - American Merchant Marine Library Association, 1931-1961 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Some small contributions by Mary French Rockefeller.
  - Libraries - Folger Memorial Library, 1931-1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Libraries - General Theological Library, 1922-1950 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Annual $100 John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions.
  - Libraries - Germanistic Society of America, 1924-1928, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions toward distribution of periodicals.
  - Libraries - New York Society Library, 1927, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Libraries - Redwood Library and Athenaeum, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    Newport, Rhode Island.
  - Libraries - Tarrytown Library, 1921-1925 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Libraries - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1949-1960 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Information on activities of library; Nelson A. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. become fellows of the library, 1949. Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributions. Correspondents include Nelson A. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    183.10
  - Libraries - Pierpont Morgan Library, 1949-1960 (Box 4, Folder 0032A)
    David Rockefeller becomes fellow of the library, 1949. Correspondents include David Rockefeller.
  - Libraries - Pierpont Morgan Library - Contributions, 1949-1961 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    By Nelson A. Rockefeller, Laurance S. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd.
  - Libraries - Pierpont Morgan Library - Contributions, 1949-1961 (Box 4, Folder 0033A)
    By David Rockefeller.
- Memorials
  - Memorials - National McKinley Birthplace Memorial Association, c. 1916-1918 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Two bound booklets.
    162
  - Memorials - National McKinley Birthplace Memorial Association, 1901-1933 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    John D. Rockefeller contributes $5,000 to Memorial; declines request for bust of himself to be placed in Memorial. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Memorials - Louis Pasteur Memorial, 1911-1924 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    John D. Rockefeller purchases Pasteur's home for use as Memorial Museum, 1912; letters of appreciation. Centennial celebration of Pasteurs birth. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Simon Flexner, Rufus Cole, Jerome Greene.
    162.5
  - Memorials - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Association, 1912-1936 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Early appeals declined; 1930; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gives $5,000 to Association. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard.
    162.2
  - Memorials - Anti-Race Track Gambling Campaign, 1908-1911 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    In 1910-1911, John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. give $230 to campaign.
    [162]
  - Memorials - Immigrant Guide and Transfer, 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made small contributions.
    162 or 63.2
  - Memorials - Lincoln Farm Association, 1907-1911 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    John D. Rockefeller made small contribution to purchase of Lincoln birthplace.
  - Memorials - Sane New Year's Eve Celebration, 1912-1916 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made small contribution.
    162 or 160
  - Memorials - World Missionary Conference, 1909-1910 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $1,000.
  - Memorials - Gaynor Hospital Fund, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $200.
  - Memorials - Bethel and Hospital, Conneaut, Ohio, 1898-1900 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    John D. Rockefeller contribution.
  - Memorials - Hewitt Memorial, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    John D. Rockefeller gave $50,000 toward memorial endowment fund for Cooper Union in honor of Abram S. Hewitt.
  - Memorials - Elbert Hubbard, 1913-1915 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Memorials - Robert Fulton and Hudson Fulton Celebration, 1906-1909 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    John D. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribute to statue of Fulton and 1909 celebration.
  - Memorials - Andrew H. Green Memorial Association, 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Memorial entrance to Central Park; John D. Rockefeller gave $1,000.
  - Memorials - Edward Everett Hale, 1911-1912 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    John D. Rockefeller gives $1,000 toward cost of statue.
  - Memorials - Longfellow National Memorial Association, 1908 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    John D. Rockefeller gives $100 for statue.
    162 or 162.4
  - Memorials - Shakespeare Memorial Theatre and Foundation, 1923-1957 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution in 1923 to English Memorial Fund; 1927, gave $500,000 for rebuilding theatre after fire. Reports on opening of new theatre. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur Woods, Arthur W. Packard.
    162.3
  - Memorials - Shakespeare Memorial Theatre and Foundation - Pledges and Payments, 1923-1939 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Memorials - Stone Mountain Memorial Association, 1925-1936 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. honorary member of committee to help distribute memorial coins; buys $5,000 of the coins; contributes $5,000 for sculpting, and promises more if Union Generals worked into scheme. This was not done; memorial was not completed. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. M. Randolph.
    162.4